<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>phd | μβ</title>
    <link>https://matbesancon.xyz/tag/phd/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://matbesancon.xyz/tag/phd/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>phd</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://matbesancon.xyz/media/icon_hu7565e292f0a230f950fabd03a1d7dda9_12642_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>phd</title>
      <link>https://matbesancon.xyz/tag/phd/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Graduate Winter/Summer Schools in Optimization - 2023</title>
      <link>https://matbesancon.xyz/post/2023-01-schools23/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://matbesancon.xyz/post/2023-01-schools23/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post collects a partial list of winter and summer schools for 2023/2024, directly inspired by
&lt;a href=&#34;https://thiagoserra.com/2020/01/19/summer-2020-schools-on-algorithms-data-science-machine-learning-networks-optimization-transportation-and-other-relevant-topics-in-operations-research/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the ones compiled by Thiago Serra&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none  &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#winter-2023&#34;&gt;Winter 2023&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#summer-2023&#34;&gt;Summer 2023&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#autumn-2023&#34;&gt;Autumn 2023&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#winter-2024&#34;&gt;Winter 2024&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;winter-2023&#34;&gt;Winter 2023&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Winter School of &lt;a href=&#34;https://ss.amsi.org.au/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;AMSI&lt;/a&gt;, 9th January, Melbourne, Australia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;summer-2023&#34;&gt;Summer 2023&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spring School on &lt;a href=&#34;https://epit2023.sciencesconf.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Complexity&lt;/a&gt;, 12th June, Oléron, France&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Summer School on &lt;a href=&#34;https://ssaad2023.sciencesconf.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Automatic Algorithm Design 2023&lt;/a&gt;, 12th June, Villeneuve d&amp;rsquo;Ascq, France&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Summer School of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.numta.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;NUMERICAL COMPUTATIONS: THEORY AND ALGORITHMS&lt;/a&gt;, 14th June, Calabria, Italy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Summer School of &lt;a href=&#34;https://optimization.discovery.wisc.edu/ipco-2023-madison/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;IPCO&lt;/a&gt;, 19th June, Madison, Wisconsin, US&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Summer School of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fernuni-hagen.de/produktion-logistik/forschung/veranstaltungen/PhD_Summer_School.shtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PhD Summer School on Sustainable Supply Chains&lt;/a&gt;, 29th June, Hagen, Germany&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gene Golub SIAM Summer School on &lt;a href=&#34;https://wordpress.lehigh.edu/siamquantum&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Quantum Computing and Optimization&lt;/a&gt; , 30th July, Lehigh, PA, US&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Summer School of &lt;a href=&#34;https://school.a4cp.org/summer2023/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Machine Learning for Constraint Programming&lt;/a&gt; 10th July, Leuven, Belgium&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Summer School of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bilevelconference2023.org/summer-school&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bilevel Optimization&lt;/a&gt; conference, 8th August, Southampton, UK&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;autumn-2023&#34;&gt;Autumn 2023&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Autumn School on Constrained Optimization in Machine Learning, ALOP, University of Trier&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Autumn School of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.natcor.ac.uk/courses/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;NATCOR&lt;/a&gt; on Combinatorial Optimization, 11th September, University of Southampton, UK&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I missed your favourite school for 2023 and first quarter 2024, open a pull request and modify &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/matbesancon/hugo-site/blob/master/content/post/2023-01-schools23.markdown&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this file&lt;/a&gt;.
Thanks to Mark Turner and Joao Dionisio for pointing out some of these!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;winter-2024&#34;&gt;Winter 2024&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Winter School on &lt;a href=&#34;https://netopt2024.campus.ciencias.ulisboa.pt/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Network Optimization&lt;/a&gt;, Estoril, Portugal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bringing a PhD to the finishing line</title>
      <link>https://matbesancon.xyz/post/2021-04-02-phdone/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://matbesancon.xyz/post/2021-04-02-phdone/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none  &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#plan-organize-prioritize-ruthlessly&#34;&gt;Plan, organize, prioritize ruthlessly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#mind-the-change-blindness-on-your-research&#34;&gt;Mind the change blindness on your research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#thesis-ownership&#34;&gt;Thesis ownership&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last December, I defended my doctoral dissertation and finished the last steps towards the completion of my double PhD.
I am only writing about it now because the experience left me drained but also extremely busy
with things I had been putting off for a while.
Now that a quarter of 2021 has vanished before me, we get to the point where putting it off for longer means forgetting about it.
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;und&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;▓▓▓▓░░░░░░░░░░░ 25%&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Year Progress (@year_progress) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/year_progress/status/1377863380095107072?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;April 2, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The major reasons for not doing this earlier are banality and messiness. Banality because many have written great pieces about
different stages of the PhD process, even better when written by people from awarding institutions
who see cohorts succeed and fail every year.
Still, I believe there are few angles that I would have liked to see stressed more and earlier, for me or others.
Messiness because several thoughts had been in the back of my mind, discussed with others, and were still looming around without much structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The end of a PhD is notoriously hard and you are mostly fighting against yourself, the excitement from the beginning
is gone and any trick could be taken to smoothen this. Here are some things that worked not only well,
but more than I would have expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;plan-organize-prioritize-ruthlessly&#34;&gt;Plan, organize, prioritize ruthlessly&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a general line of advice for the whole doctoral journey, even more important for the end.
The finishing process by the French institutions jointly awarding my degree was ridiculously complex with many steps
involving back-and-forth with multiple documents and actors.
I would have loved to illustrate this with the diagram for the procedure at my institution
but that might be needlessly targeting them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With such a mess, it is easy to lose focus of the scientific part and waste your time on paperwork.
Remember this needs to be done but is low-priority. Do it when you are low on energy and focus, when you are
tired or finish a work sprint, do not waste the valuable hours of your day on papers. Check the hard deadlines,
is it in quite some time? Put it in a calendar and forget about it until you have time or no choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My point here is: &lt;strong&gt;no PhD&lt;/strong&gt; is awarded for being good at filling the paperwork and it should not be on the top of your mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were notoriously joking in the French research team about the time it took me to get properly enrolled in the first year.
It could have been faster if I had spent more time and attention on it, in that case, go several
times to the graduate administration offices. In retrospect, considering it low-priority and
focusing on research before working the admin into my schedule was perfectly fine and let me focus
on research much faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Towards the end, prioritizing means constantly asking &amp;ldquo;Can I put this off until after my defence / my dissertation hand-out?&amp;rdquo;.
If not, can you squeeze it in a time frame where it is not penalizing your research? If yes, put it in a
calendar and forget about it. Don&amp;rsquo;t hesitate to consider this approach even for personal stuff you consider or know represents
efforts. Seeing family, looking for a place for your next position, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last sprint is fairly stressful, being ruthless on your priorities helps not being too hard on yourself.
Setting reasonable short-term objectives is a great way to make progress. One of the most productive decisions
I took was accepting to go on vacation in southern France for a week with friends. I had writing hours set
every day (rarely more than two) and activities the rest of the time. I probably got at least as much done as
I would have had stuck in my apartment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;mind-the-change-blindness-on-your-research&#34;&gt;Mind the change blindness on your research&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will refer throughout this post to the introduction, context, literature review and conclusion of the dissertation
as the &lt;strong&gt;outer parts&lt;/strong&gt; and the core contribution chapters as the &lt;strong&gt;inner parts&lt;/strong&gt; of the thesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While writing the outer parts of your dissertation, mind the change blindness, this perception &amp;ldquo;bug&amp;rdquo;
that lets us unaware of things that changed throughout a period.
In this case, you have become an expert on your research topic, despite what the imposter syndrome might be saying.
This also implies that you always have a mental picture of facts and ideas related to your research that have
become part of your everyday work.
The reader does not have the same years of work on the research topic, even if they are in your domain.
Highlight the contributions, more than you would have in an informal chat. Do not hesitate to write something
down in the outer parts even if it seems obvious. For readers who have not looked at the problem, show why it
is interesting. In some cultures, boasting about your results or achievements is quickly frowned upon;
in the dissertation though, resist the urge to minimize them. It is not unscientific to highlight that your work is
new, important, or opening new lines of research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The feeling I often had when writing the outer parts of the dissertation is that my point was redundant with
what was already in other places of the thesis, specifically in the inner parts.
But when reading the introduction, I will expect to get some understanding of the domain, its challenges and
open questions, how others have addressed questions similar to those of the thesis.
It is normal to have some redundancy with the explanation of a core contribution two or three chapters down the line.
In the conclusion, I do not want (just) the rehashed summary of each chapter of the inner parts
but would love to see a more critical view of the angle that has been taken on the research question, openings
on connected areas, how it could have been from a different perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give a rough idea of how I spent my last months, I handed out the manuscript at the end of September.
Starting in May and for most of the summer, I focused on the outer parts, thinking about how to structure and articulate
the introduction and literature review. The core concern that made me rework things several times was to make
these outer parts accessible and interesting for readers outside my immediate domain, or even outside research but
still with the appropriate technical background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A personal opinion &amp;amp; side-note: scientific outreach and communication is great, but a thesis is not the best place
for it, it just brings conflicting objectives and additional efforts, not every piece should be targeting any untrained reader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;thesis-ownership&#34;&gt;Thesis ownership&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last line of advice I will give is on owning your results and doctoral work.
I already had some thoughts on this &lt;a href=&#34;https://matbesancon.xyz/post/2018-09-27-year-in-phd/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;after one year into the PhD&lt;/a&gt;.
Ownership of one&amp;rsquo;s PhD topic may be the single most important factor for enjoying your doctoral research
and essential to turn into a great researcher in the long run.
Reading this post from some places, this thought may seem oddly obvious.
However, while exchanging with many doctoral candidates and reading the tone of some advisors,
I saw there is a strong conception, especially in France, that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the PhD candidate is working &lt;strong&gt;for&lt;/strong&gt; the advisor and that the PhD will follow;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the advisor is responsible for the scientific choices taken.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second point goes for the better and worse aspects, and would come with reactions as &amp;ldquo;what was the advisor thinking&amp;rdquo;
whenever some researchers see something they don&amp;rsquo;t agree with in some work done by a PhD candidate, as if the person
could not also be held responsible for their actions.
But because it implies it is the responsibility of the advisor to define and adjust the research direction,
such a line of thought is preventing PhD candidates to take ownership of their topic and research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This issue is tricky because it brings the connected subject of how PhDs are funded.
Although I love discussing it, I thought for a while about whether to write about it.
Because of the way PhDs are funded in some domains, the doctoral candidate is sometimes
considered as the person recruited to fill a particular role in the lab.
This does not help gain autonomy and a sense of ownership.
And because the funding process is determined by the institution or nationally, there isn&amp;rsquo;t much
advisors or candidates can do. What both can though is shifting the perspective on work ownership.
Regardless of how autonomous you felt during the PhD, the last sprint is the time to step it up.
It will be your name on the dissertation, associated with everything from abstract to appendix and on the defence slides;
it is your work and research profile being evaluated.
This means you should be absolutely comfortable with everything in there and be able to take credit and
blame for it, considering your advisors out of the equations during the defence.
If they still need to help you by then, something went wrong along the way.
Ownership of the decision is especially important and tricky for PhDs
carried out with(in) industrial research partners (CIFRE in France or similar programs).
Not all decisions on the investigation may be yours but you will need to justify them scientifically
in front of examiners if they are in your doctoral work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will finish with a last random fact on ownership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 1st-year PhD student recently told a group of other PhDs about an email from their advisor,
where they harshly explained that it is up to the student to reach out when they struggle,
have questions or need a meeting, also suggesting that if the advisors asked
the student for a meeting, that would be a &amp;ldquo;we need to talk&amp;rdquo; situation.
The tone of the email was fairly brutal, arguing the student had no clue on
how research works, who had which responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few opinions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The tone of the email was plain wrong. I cannot use direct quotes to protect the PhD student, but being overly harsh on your subordinates to convey ideas just shows poor self-control (and this was in written form).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The 1st year PhD student not knowing about the way academia works should be obvious, even more for someone
who has advising experience. The advisor should have realized when writing this email that this shows at best their failure
at onboarding the student in academia and explain its &lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt; unspoken rules.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This last point is where I diverged from the opinion of others who heard the student&amp;rsquo;s story: despite poor form and failed mentoring,
the advisor is right in essence and the message they gave is best given early and explicitly as they did than figured out (or not)
by the student much later in the process. This is even more the case in Corona times where 1st-year students have never
been exposed to the research environment as it used to exist.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I wrote before, the advisor is not a boss as you would think of in a company,
a closer metaphor would be an investor in time, lab resources, funding and reputation.
This model is not perfect but better aligned with productive research relationships
than the subordinate model I&amp;rsquo;ve often seen in some circles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Header photo credit:&lt;br&gt;
Richard Dykes on Unsplash&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coping with a confined PhD, a naive report</title>
      <link>https://matbesancon.xyz/post/2020-03-26-confined-phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://matbesancon.xyz/post/2020-03-26-confined-phd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the luxuries of a PhD in applied maths / computer science is the
possibility to work from home. By possibility, I imply both the technical
feasibility (my project does not require special equipment), and social
acceptability (I never worked in labs enforcing presenteeism).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, working from home or from my usual corner coffee shop once every other week
is very different from these exceptional circumstances.
I should also highlight I do not have to take care of children or sick family members,
which comes as a priority, big congrats to those who manage it. This post should not
be seen as how things should be done, simply how I cope and as a list of ideas
to pick from if you are in a similar situation. The context is also very
special for me as I just moved to the UK for an academic visit at the University
of Edinburgh, I had just settled at a new city, flat and office when things
started to escalate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;🎉🏴󠁧󠁢󠁳󠁣󠁴󠁿&lt;br&gt;With an apartment found and tickets bought, this is now official, I&amp;#39;ll be in Edinburgh in March &amp;amp; April for an academic visit at @UoEMaths ERGO&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mathieu Besançon (@matbesancon) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/matbesancon/status/1231514372729688064?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;February 23, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I decided to stay in Edinburgh instead of coming back to France because the trip
itself would be irresponsible, travelling through the UK, sleeping in London and
then crossing the border with continental Europe, but also because I was settled
in comfortably enough to spend the rough months of the epidemic here.
However, this meant adjusting in different ways.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none  &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#overall-routine&#34;&gt;Overall routine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#social-media-and-work-breaks&#34;&gt;Social media and work breaks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#broadening-work-activities&#34;&gt;Broadening work activities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#setup-and-spacial-separation&#34;&gt;Setup and spacial separation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#virtual-conferences-and-social-aspects&#34;&gt;Virtual conferences and social aspects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#keeping-your-locals-afloat&#34;&gt;Keeping your locals afloat&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#we-got-this&#34;&gt;We got this&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;overall-routine&#34;&gt;Overall routine&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being in Europe with many friends &amp;amp; contacts in North America, I used the
circumstances to slightly shift my day, waking up between 8.30 and 9.15, and
going to bed a bit later, sharing more hours of the day with them. This would
normally be more complicated with things to attend to where I am, but allow me
to attend European late morning and afternoon remote events, North-American
morning and early-afternoon events. I take a quick breakfast in the kitchen
(no hot drink), make a batch of tea or coffee to keep while at my desk. I use
the morning to catch up on emails, work on research, writing code and prose
(with breaks, see below). I do not go back to eat while not hungry, and not before 1.30PM.
The afternoon is a blend of research work and semi-work-related activities.
I usually have figured out something to cook by the end of the day, depending on
how much I estimate this will take I start late-afternoon or early evening.
Depending on the mood and tasks, I work a bit after dinner, before closing all
work tabs and windows (yes, all) to switch to leisure time, including films,
calling people, etc. I keep at least one hour at the end of the day for reading,
these days fiction (the Poppy War, the Alienist and Death in the East at the moment),
and only in paper versions, since I don&amp;rsquo;t have a reader and I get enough screen
time in the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;social-media-and-work-breaks&#34;&gt;Social media and work breaks&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First things first, these things suck up your time and attention the rest of the
year, now they also build up your anxiety like never before. I&amp;rsquo;m not telling you
to resist (I don&amp;rsquo;t), just to separate the time where you work from the social
media time in small blocks; &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;pomodoro&lt;/a&gt;
is your friend there. With this setting, being distracted is okay, when you
suddenly find yourself on non-work related things, just stop the work timer,
take your break, and restart it when you are ready to restart.
My breaks vary between 5 and 30 minutes, either texting friends, reading
non-work news articles, scrolling or playing mines:
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Well how is YOUR discovery of gravity going? &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/Q8jaDPq6Tg&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/Q8jaDPq6Tg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mathieu Besançon (@matbesancon) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/matbesancon/status/1243125633800114177?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;March 26, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of the time, I close distracting browser tabs (including emails) and
toss my phone out of reach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;broadening-work-activities&#34;&gt;Broadening work activities&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Staying focused on work is clearly harder; one way to cope with it is to broaden
work activities and even if it does not serve you in the short term, consider it
work, no need to drown in guilt. My semi-work activities include open-source software,
reading papers and books in my domain but not directly relevant to my research,
following MOOCs, even on some things I assume I already know to see a different
perspective. You may have noticed lots of university seminars are maintained
in an online format. Since you do not need to run to the building on the other
side of the campus, it can be a good opportunity to spend 45 minutes on other
topics for your general scientific culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;setup-and-spacial-separation&#34;&gt;Setup and spacial separation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This section is to take with a pinch of salt, it assumes some financial comfort
and a big enough flat. Early in the epidemic when it felt like we were going for
gradual home isolation, I started setting up my office in a way that felt good,
not for two hours in the evening any more, but for 8+ hours in the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://matbesancon.xyz/img/posts/office.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the second monitor.
I don&amp;rsquo;t think more than two active screens is necessary, but it may vary with
activities, beware of excessive multi-tasking though.
The only new thing I invested in is a keyboard,
which I had not brought to the UK. It&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.drevo.net/product/keyboard/gramr&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;DREVO Gramr&lt;/a&gt;
mechanical keyboard with brown switches, reasonably priced and with a nice-enough
touch. It also gave me the opportunity to finally re-switch to qwerty layout and stick to it.
The biggest point for me of having an external keyboard is improving my posture.
My screens are further away and higher thanks to few books, allowing me to keep
my back straighter and relax my eyes.
Working with a laptop alone is nice for few hours in a coffee shop or on a couch,
but terrible for your eyes, arms, hands and back, &lt;strong&gt;forget the lap of laptop&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spatial separation is fairly simple: work remains at my desk, I keep the
living room for eating, drinks, films, chatting with my flatmate. If you have an
office space to separate it from your bedroom, even better. This is also why I
cannot blame Parisians leaving the capital for family houses, the lifestyle is
not adapted to actually living in your $15m^2$ flat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;virtual-conferences-and-social-aspects&#34;&gt;Virtual conferences and social aspects&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a discussion on the remote thesis during the epidemic on the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.grandlabo.com/sos-telethese-continuer-sa-these-en-plein-confinement-coronavirus/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Grand Labo&lt;/a&gt; (in French).
Among different subjects, I chose to speak of something which may appear very
privileged (and is to some extent), which is the impact of cancelled academic
events (conferences, workshops, seminars), especially on young academics, in
which I include everyone being evaluated on their work now for a future position
or promotion (master&amp;rsquo;s, PhDs, postdoctoral researchers, professors subject to
the tenure clock).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The summary of the discussion is that scientific aspects of
the events can be emulated though online seminars, but the networking aspects
are much harder. The reason young academics are more heavily impacted is because
we are the ones looking for contacts for what we will do afterwards, and both
discovering and getting in touch with those contacts depends on such events.
I do not have a perfect solution for this, and I&amp;rsquo;m not sure there is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;keeping-your-locals-afloat&#34;&gt;Keeping your locals afloat&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again this section is to take relatively to what you can afford. If you are not
financially comfortable (and this is a post for PhDs so it might very well be the
case, feel free to pick the pieces you want). One thing that will happen with
everything shut down is that businesses and service workers that depend on a local
activity will suffer. For tech workers, here is a great thread, although
US-centric so some of the consequences will be hopefully nuanced in your country:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;The US govt has failed to contain this outbreak&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It&amp;#39;s now up to us, as individuals, to protect and support our communities&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Techies and other financially privileged people, this thread is for YOU:&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; bletchley punk (@alicegoldfuss) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/alicegoldfuss/status/1239621791145807882?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;March 16, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Restaurants&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;- Find out if your local faves are providing sick leave and pay for their workers. Shame them into doing it.&lt;br&gt;- Order delivery to keep people paid&lt;br&gt;- Have delivery drops in your lobby or stoop for their protection&lt;br&gt;- TIP DIGITALLY don&amp;#39;t make them touch your grubby cash&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; bletchley punk (@alicegoldfuss) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/alicegoldfuss/status/1239622445578907648?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;March 16, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key point of this thread is your local restaurant, bar, pub. You do not want
it closed and replaced by a chain (I assume?), and you do not want the employees
that made it a great place without a job in these times where finding a new one
will be hard. Check if they do delivery and / or take-away, at least allow yourself
one treat a week, plus for special occasions
(article submitted, came back from review, published, accepted, pushed as preprint).
Contact them to know if they kept their staff, favour the ones who did.
If they offer vouchers to use when they re-open, take some, otherwise suggest
them so. This also goes for corner coffee &amp;amp; tea shop, they may still do take-away
and need you now. I am trying to do so in Edinburgh, on the recommendations of my
flatmates, friends and locals on &lt;a href=&#34;https://reddit.com/r/Edinburgh/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt;,
while I hope others do the same in my neighbourhood in Lille.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;we-got-this&#34;&gt;We got this&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing that was highlighted in the PhD panel with the Grand Labo was the
overwhelming guilt, which is always latent in academia and comes out even stronger
in these times. Keep in mind this is some never-seen event, re-writing much of
how we live, work and socialize. Some parts are crisis measures that will gradually
fade away, but some aspects will remain after the shock. Even coping at our best
does not make the situation remotely &amp;ldquo;fine&amp;rdquo; for many of us, but we got this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want more and better tips on working from home for tech workers in the epidemic time,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.alicegoldfuss.com/work-in-the-time-of-corona/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;, from the
same author as the restaurant recommendations above, is worth it.
If you read French, feel free to also check this thread:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;fr&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;[THREAD DOCTORAT]&lt;br&gt;Bonjour à tous, comme la plupart des doctorants du territoires nous avons été encouragés à faire du télétravail à partir de lundi, puis en quelques heures aujourd’hui la situation s’est dégradée. Nous ne pouvons plus accéder à nos laboratoire ,à nos manips, rien&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Dr. Mathilde 👩🏼‍💻 (@BienDansMaThese) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BienDansMaThese/status/1239347768562499586?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;March 16, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;where Mathilde documents the progress and of setting up a workflow and new
habits in these bizarre times, that fell on academia in France with little warning
or preparation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A year in PhD</title>
      <link>https://matbesancon.xyz/post/2018-09-27-year-in-phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://matbesancon.xyz/post/2018-09-27-year-in-phd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, it&amp;rsquo;s been a bit more than a year since I took a flight to Montréal to
start a PhD on mathematical optimization &amp;amp; game theory for smart grids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the rush of summer conferences, and my return to France
for a part of my PhD at INRIA Lille, it is a good time to take a step back
and think of what has been going on and what is coming next. I&amp;rsquo;ll also answer
some common questions I had in a more thoughtful way than I can in a
bar conversation/family dinner. Maybe this can also help other PhD students seeing
we are not in the same boat, but they all still look alike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TL;DR&lt;/strong&gt;: a PhD is not studies in the sense you think, and it&amp;rsquo;s not a job either,
these mental models will not help much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;so-when-are-you-going-to-finish&#34;&gt;So, when are you going to finish?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know, when are you going to finish your job? It doesn&amp;rsquo;t look
like it&amp;rsquo;s been moving that much recently. Or when will this company
you&amp;rsquo;re building be &amp;ldquo;finished&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These questions are similar, really. A research subject is rarely isolated,
don&amp;rsquo;t see this as emptying a 4-year bowl of soup. It&amp;rsquo;s more like picking
berries: you grab one, then the next, which is close enough, oh and this one
is nice, but a bit further, I&amp;rsquo;ll have to stretch my arm a bit more to reach it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://matbesancon.xyz/img/posts/phd-year/blueberries.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
[1]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had some interesting discussions in Montréal about when and how to know
you should bring your PhD to a conclusion. And the answer should always be
that it depends what your objectives are, if you want to include this last
project in the PhD. So no, I don&amp;rsquo;t know when I will finish, because if every
step was predictable in terms of duration and success, it would not be a PhD or
even research, what I do know is that I don&amp;rsquo;t want to block interesting projects
or leave only half-explored research trails because &amp;ldquo;3 years is plenty&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;it-must-feel-weird-getting-back-to-university&#34;&gt;It must feel weird, getting back to university&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It does, but not how you imagine. I was previously at
&lt;a href=&#34;https://matbesancon.xyz/post/2016-08-11-back-to-startup/&#34;&gt;a startup&lt;/a&gt; for a while.
What I was used to is a great autonomy in execution. What the
PhD is about is adding self-determination of the objectives,
expected results, and means. It does not mean I&amp;rsquo;m working alone
while I was in a team before, it means the degree of ownership
of successes and failures is much higher, try to picture the
three following sentences in a conversation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;I was at a startup before, it failed and I moved on to XYZ.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;I started a PhD but didn&amp;rsquo;t get through, then moved on to XYZ.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;I built a company, it failed, now I&amp;rsquo;m working on XYZ.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It depends on the relationship to failure the person has in front of
you, but for those I know, (1) is just an external cause, while (2)
and (3) are personal failures, that&amp;rsquo;s ownership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest conclusion I made roughly after 6 months in is that a
single-founder startup is one of the closest mental models to keep
during the PhD, which explains several things, like inability to
explain exactly what you do to your family and friends, imposter
syndrome or procrastination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;so-you-get-paid-enough-to-buy-noodles&#34;&gt;So you get paid enough to buy noodles?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, I&amp;rsquo;m living quite well thanks, I can even afford fancying
my noodles, but let&amp;rsquo;s dig deeper on the matter of €/$/£.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/strong&gt;: my PhD is between applied maths &amp;amp; computer science, I know
all majors are not that financially comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://matbesancon.xyz/img/posts/phd-year/noodles.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
[2]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also know it&amp;rsquo;s considered rude to talk about money in some cultures,
including France, especially if you&amp;rsquo;re not complaining; so yes, I&amp;rsquo;ll
be rude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I&amp;rsquo;m in France, I&amp;rsquo;m paid slightly less than some engineers with the same
level of qualification. The difference is higher if I&amp;rsquo;m comparing to what
I would have had on Data Science, applied maths and software development
positions. The difference between what I would earn and the scholarship
is higher in Canada. Still, like I said, I can live without watching
my bank account towards the end of the month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest danger of getting money monthly is thinking of it as a salary,
meaning you&amp;rsquo;re thinking of the PhD as a job, meaning you&amp;rsquo;re thinking of
yourself as an employee. On the paper, the money I get in France is a salary
from my research institute, but one should keep in mind this is only on paper,
the danger is to get the wrong mindset: &lt;strong&gt;think of yourself as a single person
carrying a project, not an employee&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People often argue that they have a research director, who is de facto their boss.
I don&amp;rsquo;t think this is the case, directors choose project proposals and people
to carry them out (the order of this choice varies). They choose to invest
time, effort and money from their structure into this person+project pair,
without dictating to the letter what the outcomes of the projects are.
Their retribution for this exchange is a partial ownership in the outcomes
of the project (publications, conferences, software).
Sounds familiar? Yes I&amp;rsquo;m looking at the Wikipedia
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Venture_capital&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;page on Venture Capital&lt;/a&gt;.
Let&amp;rsquo;s dig deeper: thesis directors invest this time, money and energy in
areas they are familiar with, they have worked in and/or have mentored other
people on. This sounds like the VC firms&amp;rsquo; investment theses.
Read &lt;a href=&#34;https://a16z.com/2016/08/20/why-software-is-eating-the-world/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;these&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://hackernoon.com/the-birth-of-a-venture-capital-investment-thesis-afd2903ae12&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;two&lt;/a&gt;
articles to see a more proper definition and examples of investment theses
but I hope you&amp;rsquo;ll get my point: PhDs are not R&amp;amp;D employees and directors are
not &amp;ldquo;bosses&amp;rdquo;. If you have friends familiar with how startups work, this should
be fine to explain. If you&amp;rsquo;re talking to people who have been employees their
whole life in traditional structures, I have not yet found a clear and simple
way to explain the situation in a casual conversation, let me know if you have
something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;so-back-to-being-a-student-heh&#34;&gt;So, back to being a student heh?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This image is much easier to correct. On the paper this is true,
a PhD has a student status, even when working close with/in
companies like in Germany, Denmark or France CIFRE theses.
Some people will ask this genuinely because they still picture their
undergraduate years and think you&amp;rsquo;re back to this.
So, it&amp;rsquo;s true, I&amp;rsquo;m taking courses, mostly because I find them
interesting and keeping learning things is a bit of a &lt;em&gt;raison d&amp;rsquo;être&lt;/em&gt;.
But I was also doing so while working, using online courses platform like
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Coursera&lt;/a&gt; or
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fun-mooc.fr/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;France Université Numérique&lt;/a&gt;, going to meetups,
reading and writing blog posts. So the thing that changed is maybe the part
of my time dedicated to learning which got higher than when employed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now about the second category of people asking this question, yeah those one.
In general, the points discussed above are enough as an explanation,
but if the tone is really about trolling, which can happen, reverse the question:
&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Yeah I&amp;rsquo;m a student, I&amp;rsquo;m learning stuff every day. Wait you&amp;rsquo;re not?
Exactly the stagnation I don&amp;rsquo;t want in my life.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is it mean? Maybe, but the point is not to &amp;ldquo;win&amp;rdquo; a conversation, it&amp;rsquo;s about
shutting down the perpetration of imposter syndrome, own the uniqueness of
your status, both the good and the bad bits. None should be made feel inferior
because they didn&amp;rsquo;t take the conventional, safe and socially accepted path of
the 9-17 workday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;re-thinking-my-values--priorities&#34;&gt;Re-thinking my values &amp;amp; priorities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve written about values &lt;a href=&#34;https://matbesancon.xyz/post/2016-10-7-company-values/&#34;&gt;two years ago&lt;/a&gt;
in the context of a company trying to define who they are.
This is a complex topic, about discovering and understanding what the
group prioritizes collectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the owner of your project and of your time and resources, it&amp;rsquo;s up to you to define
what is important. This begins with what is measured for success. Coming to academia
from another &lt;em&gt;milieu&lt;/em&gt;, I was not used to the process of publishing in peer-reviewed
journals. First position I&amp;rsquo;ll take and try to maintain: &lt;strong&gt;the measures of academic
success are broken, or at least imperfect&lt;/strong&gt; (reach out to future-me if I change my mind).
One example of this is research software.
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Paraphrasing &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mgymrek?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@mgymrek&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Your paper is cited outside of your field in one semi-related paragraph: *counts towards your career progression*&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Your academic software package has 100 stars on GitHub: *counts for nothing*&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Something is wrong here 😐 &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/jsm2018?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#jsm2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Sean Kross, PhD (@seankross) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/seankross/status/1024059834654588929?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 30, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Had my &amp;quot;software is part of the research process&amp;quot; argument with an academic who wanted to use software to generate results but didn&amp;#39;t want to &amp;quot;concentrate on it too much&amp;quot;. I should start counting how many times I go through this and throw a party when I get to a million.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Simon Hettrick (@sjh5000) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/sjh5000/status/1043112943372644353?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;September 21, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


If you can, watch
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/walkingrandomly&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mike Croucher&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s excellent
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8ZSaAM8hhJ4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt; at JuliaCon 2018 for more
depth on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The consequence of ignoring software as a valuable result of research is
pretty straight-forward: proprietary software all over.
It&amp;rsquo;s changing in scientific computing, statistics and other fields with
the rise of Julia, R, Python. My domain, mathematical optimization, is
still behind with dominant solvers (the software doing the actual work)
and lots of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Algebraic_modeling_language&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Algebraic Modeling Languages&lt;/a&gt;
(the front-end to interact with the solver) being proprietary.
The last part is &lt;a href=&#34;https://numfocus.org/project/jump&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;changing&lt;/a&gt;,
the first one is still tough.
My point is that people behind software you&amp;rsquo;re
using everyday contribute way more to the success of your PhD than this
obscure paper you cite because the review committee asked you to.
If your university is giving thousands in commercial licenses and
millions in access to paper, maybe you should make them donate both time
and money to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flipcause.com/secure/cause_pdetails/MjM2OA==&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;tools&lt;/a&gt;
you&amp;rsquo;re using. Yes all of &lt;a href=&#34;https://donate.wikimedia.org/wiki/WMFJA1/en/US&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;them&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been involved in the Julia community, especially within the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/JuliaGraphs/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;JuliaGraphs&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/JuliaStats/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;JuliaStats&lt;/a&gt; ecosystems, mostly because these
are subjects I understand (at least a bit) and/or used.
Key take-away:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reporting issues you have and contributing to improve the documentation
is as valuable as writing code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;so-its-been-a-year&#34;&gt;So&amp;hellip; it&amp;rsquo;s been a year&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I&amp;rsquo;m still learning (understand making mistakes, getting stuck, etc),
one of the reasons I had to learn more is not coming from a background
in maths, nor from a research-oriented degree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reach out any way you prefer, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/matbesancon&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://matbesancon.xyz/#contact&#34;&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;. Of course some things I&amp;rsquo;ve written are related
to my situation, I&amp;rsquo;d be interested to know how it relates or not to yours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Image sources:&lt;br&gt;
[1] &lt;a href=&#34;https://pxhere.com/en/photo/571187&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://pxhere.com/en/photo/571187&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
[2] &lt;a href=&#34;https://pixabay.com/en/noodles-thailand-food-thai-2693009/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://pixabay.com/en/noodles-thailand-food-thai-2693009/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Switching my work flow to Pomodoro for grad studies - part I: motivation  </title>
      <link>https://matbesancon.xyz/post/2017-10-19-tomate-cli/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://matbesancon.xyz/post/2017-10-19-tomate-cli/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The start of my journey as a PhD student last September was a big step, but
also an opportunity to review and improve my working habits. My day time
had to be used properly, both for results&amp;rsquo; sake and to be able to keep
a balanced life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had been introduced to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Pomodoro technique&lt;/a&gt;
at Equisense (thanks &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CamilleSaute&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Camille&lt;/a&gt;!) but
remained skeptical as for its potential value within my work
flow at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make it short, the technique consists in the following steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decide what task should be worked on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allocate a given time to work (around 25 minutes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set a timer and get to work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the time is up, make a short pause (~5 minutes), then repeat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After 4 work sprints, take a longer break (~15-30 minutes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-was-wrong-with-that&#34;&gt;What was wrong with that?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The development, test and operation phases were generally self-determining
and lead to sprints from 20 to 120 minutes (that length isn&amp;rsquo;t surprising
for some tasks and when highly focused). These were also often
interrupted by team interactions (required concertation with members
of the tech and product team, backend-specific collaborative
problem-solving, &amp;hellip;). The main point was that
&lt;strong&gt;there are enough spontaneous interruptions of the work flow, no need to introduce an additional artificial one&lt;/strong&gt;.
As I look back, I still think this was a valid reason
not to use this technique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-has-changed&#34;&gt;What has changed?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time management as a grad student has to be un- and re-learned:
rules are different, criteria for success change and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://matbesancon.xyz/img/posts/tomate/phd_time.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time management seen by PhD comics [2]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;problem-structure-programming-at-a-startup-vs-applied-math&#34;&gt;Problem structure: programming at a startup vs. applied math&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my case, the major part of the workload switched from an
implementation-heavy to a modeling-heavy context. As such,
the work phases tend to be longer and with an heavier
cognitive load. I am not saying that programming is
easier, but I&amp;rsquo;m pretty sure mathematics almost always
requires to keep more information in mind while working
on a problem. Another opinion is that the part of
instinct to find a path towards a solution is higher
in mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While programming, there are some key techniques that
reduce the number of possible sources to a problem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Getting information on the state of the program at a given point (logging, debugging, printing to &lt;code&gt;stdout&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Testing the behavior of an isolated piece of the program with given input&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These techniques also work for scientific computing of course, but are
harder to apply to both modeling and symbolic calculus, the different
pieces of the problem have to be combined to find special structures
which allow for a resolution. More solutions also tend to come
while NOT looking at mathematical problem than for programming
problems, where solutions come either in front of the code or when
voluntarily thinking of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;team-dependent-work-vs-figure-it-out-for-yourself&#34;&gt;Team-dependent work vs. figure it out for yourself&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most startups obviously value team work, it is one of the
group skills that differentiate companies building great
things from the ones stuck in an eternal early stage.
This was even more true at Equisense where collaboration
and product development were both very synchronous by
modern standards. It had cons but ease two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speed of product development&lt;/strong&gt;. Lots of team under-estimate post-development coordination, the last meters of the sprint to have a feature ready&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Programming by constraints&lt;/strong&gt;. Because of fast interactions between the people responsible for the different components, constraints from each one is quickly communicated and the modeling process is defined accounting for them right away.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now in research, especially in applied mathematics, the work is
mostly independent, synchronization happens when working
on a joined project for instance. This means that all the
interruptions that were happening throughout the day are
now gone!
&lt;strong&gt;Nothing would stop you from working day and night without a break&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two key results of this change of work style are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work sprints are not naturally bound anymore, obviously with decreasing efficiency&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Few to no interactions interrupt the sprints either&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My conclusion was the necessity of a time management technique
and associated tools, with a low cognitive overhead and bringing
as little distraction as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From these criteria, I rejected a mobile app,
smartphones are great to bring different sources
of information and communication channels together,
not for remaining focused for hours,
&lt;strong&gt;mobile apps are designed to catch and retain attention&lt;/strong&gt;,
that&amp;rsquo;s simply part of their business model. I also rejected
web-based solutions for the constraint of firing up
a browser, amongst the heaviest pieces of software on our
modern desktops, just to start a working session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So desktop GUI or CLI it is. Even though there is the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://gnomepomodoro.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;gnomepomodoro project&lt;/a&gt;, it did not seem compatible with all
Linux desktops. At that point, I realized the amount of
work to build a Pomodoro was low, the requirements and
constraints well known, I throw ideas
together and start coding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll explain the initial development and iterations of
the app in Go in a second article, if you liked this one,
let me know!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources and images:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://pixabay.com/en/tomatoes-vegetables-red-delicious-73913&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://substance-en.etsmtl.ca/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/2.gif&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
