<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>academia on μβ</title>
    <link>https://matbesancon.github.io/tags/academia/</link>
    <description>Recent content in academia on μβ</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-ca</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019 Mathieu Besançon</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="https://matbesancon.github.io/tags/academia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A naive and incomplete guide to peer-review</title>
      <link>https://matbesancon.github.io/post/2019-02-04-article-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://matbesancon.github.io/post/2019-02-04-article-review/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the first submissions to journals, most researchers will be contacted
by editors for reviewing articles others have written. It may seem like a
daunting task, evaluating the work someone else put several months to
prepare, code, write, correct and submit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/strong&gt;: to preserve the anonymity of the reviews I made and am
making, all examples I give below are made up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main phases of my reviewing process are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is this about? Can I review it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is the paper in the scope of the journal?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are there some topics I might struggle to understand?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diving in, a first pass to get the story right&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thematic passes &amp;amp; writing the recommendations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-this-about-can-i-review-it&#34;&gt;What is this about? Can I review it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After receiving the invitation and getting the manuscript, my screening phase
consists in reading only these three elements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Title&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Abstract&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keywords&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At that point, I roughly know if it is relevant for both the journal and me
that I review it. If I feel way out of scope, I&amp;rsquo;ll reach out to the editor.
I will also quickly check the name of the authors to make sure I do not have
a conflict of interests with any of them, without looking them up on the
internet of course, the goal is to avoid bias if I know them at a personal level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: Since this only took a quick screening, it can be done in a day or two,
letting the editor know too late that you will not review increases
the time to publication which is bad for the author, the journal and scientific
publication in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;is-the-paper-in-the-scope-of-the-journal&#34;&gt;Is the paper in the scope of the journal?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At that point, I re-read the journal&amp;rsquo;s aim and scope and keep in mind the main
ideas. If I am not that familiar with it, I will also check titles and abstracts
of random papers in the last issues. This will help during the review if
there are some doubts on the manuscript being at the right spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;are-there-some-topics-i-might-struggle-to-understand&#34;&gt;Are there some topics I might struggle to understand?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I have doubts on some parts of the method or context
and can identify them, I&amp;rsquo;ll search for foundational articles and reference
text books on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, it is predictable that not all reviewers of the paper cover
the same area of expertise, especially for multi-disciplinary
journals. Still, it is always better to be comfortable with all components.
Take a case in mathematical optimization, for instance a manuscript
tackling a problem in power systems, with a game theoretical aspect and
formulating a Semi-Definite Positive model solved using a bundle method.
I might be familiar with the application (power systems) and game-theoretical
considerations in such domain, but without being an expert in SDP and even less
bundle methods. This is not a reason to refuse the role of reviewer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, not being proficient on a component can introduce a bias in the
review by putting the reviewer on the defensive:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;why do the authors need all this fuss with this thing I&amp;rsquo;ve never heard of,
why not the good all techniques like what I do&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve seen read different comments in reviews which looked a lot like this.
This is why it can be valuable to take some time to get more familiar
with shadow areas. Plus this makes reviewing a challenge and an excuse
to learn something new and connected to my area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;diving-in-a-first-pass-to-get-the-story-right&#34;&gt;Diving in, a first pass to get the story right&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At that point, I book at least two hours for a first read of the paper,
with a pen, a printed version and a notebook. I should eventually get a
tablet to take notes on the PDF instead of print-outs but for the moment,
the number of papers I am asked to review remains reasonable.
I read it through without interruptions (no phone, no open browser, no music
or music without lyrics), taking notes on the side on all things that cross
my mind.
Notes are of different types: small mistakes, remarkable points, key information
and the &amp;ldquo;interrogation queue&amp;rdquo;. This queue is inspired by developers&amp;rsquo; code review
and the most advanced metric found for it:
&lt;img src=&#34;https://matbesancon.github.io/img/posts/peer_review/wtfm.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
An element is added in the queue when something is missing for my
understanding here and has not been introduced upwards in the article.
An element is removed from the queue when an explanation for it appears
(so later in the article). Of course, any element remaining in the queue
at the end of the manuscript is a problem: it is never explained,
introduced properly. Two considerations play a role for the quality of
the paper for its ease of understanding:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How long is the queue at any point in the paper? Does it introduce too much cognitive load?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How long is the distance between the appearance of an element in the queue? (the interrogation moment) and its removal (the aha moment)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second point is easy to solve, just recommend introducing the concept
before the place in the text where the interrogation appeared.
The first point will require more work on the authors&amp;rsquo; side
to displace all explanations before the introduction of the concept/symbol,
reducing the overall cognitive load at any moment for the reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thematic-read-writing-the-recommendations&#34;&gt;Thematic read &amp;amp; writing the recommendations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the first reading round, I usually have some ideas about what are the key
axes of the review, I can start writing it up with all the small details
(typos, clumsy or vague phrasing, etc), all that is not on the structure nor on
the content. A good rule of thumb is that those minor corrections are limited
to few words in just one sentence.
After that, I write down different main axes, as for instance:
&amp;ldquo;this step of the methodology section is not detailed enough&amp;rdquo; and quote
either precise points in the text where the problem arises from and/or
recommendations for fixing it: &amp;ldquo;this or that would make the article to be reproducible&amp;rdquo;.
The deeper a problem is, the more discussion it brings, the goal is not to let
the authors stuck with a blind comment, see the following examples nobody likes reading:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Some steps in Section III seem incorrect&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How much does it cost to the reviewer to point out where and why exactly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The authors did not manage to highlight a significant part of the literature&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On which topic? What is not covered? Do you mean the authors did not cite &lt;strong&gt;your&lt;/strong&gt; article?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only after these last points am I 100% certain of the final recommendation I
will give for the manuscript, the usual options are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With the minor modifications recommended, the paper is good to be published in my opinion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some required modifications are major, re-submit for another reviewing round.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The issues raised during review are too central to fix during review rounds, the work needs a huge re-write.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After forming this opinion, if I am not too late on the deadline, I will
let myself some time off the review (a few days), and then come back to what
I wrote to be sure every comment can be understood and used by the authors to
improve the paper. Also, I want to be sure not to have written anything
too rash. Nobody wants to be &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/thirdreviewer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;that&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/YourPaperSucks&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;reviewer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though peer review is considered a pillar of modern research, it has its
history, qualities and flaws, and is fundamentally made by human beings and
does not systematically reflect a universal truth; that should be kept in mind
at all time. Also, the scientific communities should keep challenging it by
making it evolve and experimenting &lt;a href=&#34;https://elifesciences.org/articles/36545&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;new ways&lt;/a&gt;
of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theoj.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;carrying it out&lt;/a&gt;, addressing some key
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.immpressmagazine.com/peer-review-is-broken/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;flaws&lt;/a&gt;. Note that I do
not say the solutions presented in these articles are the ground truth,
all I am stating is that it is worth opening the discussion, which academia
is not doing much at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe you have other tips for reviewing papers, how do you improve your process?
Which points were too domain-dependent / idealistic? (I did warn it was a naive view)
Reach out any way you prefer, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/matbesancon&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://matbesancon.github.io/#contact&#34;&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1]
Source for the cover image:
&lt;em&gt;Journal des Savants&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Journal Des Sçavans&lt;/em&gt; in old French, considered the earliest scientific journal.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://jamesgray2.me/2016/09/06/le-journal-des-savants-1681-1699/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://jamesgray2.me/2016/09/06/le-journal-des-savants-1681-1699/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Bilevel Framework for Optimal Price-Setting of Time-and-Level-of-Use Tariffs</title>
      <link>https://matbesancon.github.io/project/tlou/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://matbesancon.github.io/project/tlou/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The pre-print of the presented work can be found on &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1809.00512&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;.
The manuscript has also been submitted and should be published in the coming months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An open-source Julia package has been released
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/matbesancon/TLOU.jl&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for other researchers to
model Time-and-Level-of-Use tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A year in PhD</title>
      <link>https://matbesancon.github.io/post/2018-09-27-year-in-phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://matbesancon.github.io/post/2018-09-27-year-in-phd/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, it&amp;rsquo;s been a bit more than a year since I took a flight to Montréal to
start a PhD on mathematical optimization &amp;amp; game theory for smart grids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the rush of summer conferences, and my return to France
for a part of my PhD at INRIA Lille, it is a good time to take a step back
and think of what has been going on and what is coming next. I&amp;rsquo;ll also answer
some common questions I had in a more thoughtful way than I can in a
bar conversation/family dinner. Maybe this can also help other PhD students seeing
we are not in the same boat, but they all still look alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TL;DR&lt;/strong&gt;: a PhD is not studies in the sense you think, and it&amp;rsquo;s not a job either,
these mental models will not help much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;so-when-are-you-going-to-finish&#34;&gt;So, when are you going to finish?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know, when are you going to finish your job? It doesn&amp;rsquo;t look
like it&amp;rsquo;s been moving that much recently. Or when will this company
you&amp;rsquo;re building be &amp;ldquo;finished&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These questions are similar, really. A research subject is rarely isolated,
don&amp;rsquo;t see this as emptying a 4-year bowl of soup. It&amp;rsquo;s more like picking
berries: you grab one, then the next, which is close enough, oh and this one
is nice, but a bit further, I&amp;rsquo;ll have to stretch my arm a bit more to reach it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://matbesancon.github.io/img/posts/phd-year/blueberries.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;[1]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had some interesting discussions in Montréal about when and how to know
you should bring your PhD to a conclusion. And the answer should always be
that it depends what your objectives are, if you want to include this last
project in the PhD. So no, I don&amp;rsquo;t know when I will finish, because if every
step was predictable in terms of duration and success, it would not be a PhD or
even research, what I do know is that I don&amp;rsquo;t want to block interesting projects
or leave only half-explored research trails because &amp;ldquo;3 years is plenty&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;it-must-feel-weird-getting-back-to-university&#34;&gt;It must feel weird, getting back to university&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does, but not how you imagine. I was previously at
&lt;a href=&#34;https://matbesancon.github.io/post/2016-08-11-back-to-startup/&#34;&gt;a startup&lt;/a&gt; for a while.
What I was used to is a great autonomy in execution. What the
PhD is about is adding self-determination of the objectives,
expected results, and means. It does not mean I&amp;rsquo;m working alone
while I was in a team before, it means the degree of ownership
of successes and failures is much higher, try to picture the
three following sentences in a conversation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;I was at a startup before, it failed and I moved on to XYZ.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;I started a PhD but didn&amp;rsquo;t get through, then moved on to XYZ.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;I built a company, it failed, now I&amp;rsquo;m working on XYZ.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It depends on the relationship to failure the person has in front of
you, but for those I know, (1) is just an external cause, while (2)
and (3) are personal failures, that&amp;rsquo;s ownership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest conclusion I made roughly after 6 months in is that a
single-founder startup is one of the closest mental models to keep
during the PhD, which explains several things, like inability to
explain exactly what you do to your family and friends, imposter
syndrome or procrastination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;so-you-get-paid-enough-to-buy-noodles&#34;&gt;So you get paid enough to buy noodles?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I&amp;rsquo;m living quite well thanks, I can even afford fancying
my noodles, but let&amp;rsquo;s dig deeper on the matter of €/$/£.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/strong&gt;: my PhD is between applied maths &amp;amp; computer science, I know
all majors are not that financially comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://matbesancon.github.io/img/posts/phd-year/noodles.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;[2]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also know it&amp;rsquo;s considered rude to talk about money in some cultures,
including France, especially if you&amp;rsquo;re not complaining; so yes, I&amp;rsquo;ll
be rude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I&amp;rsquo;m in France, I&amp;rsquo;m paid slightly less than some engineers with the same
level of qualification. The difference is higher if I&amp;rsquo;m comparing to what
I would have had on Data Science, applied maths and software development
positions. The difference between what I would earn and the scholarship
is higher in Canada. Still, like I said, I can live without watching
my bank account towards the end of the month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest danger of getting money monthly is thinking of it as a salary,
meaning you&amp;rsquo;re thinking of the PhD as a job, meaning you&amp;rsquo;re thinking of
yourself as an employee. On the paper, the money I get in France is a salary
from my research institute, but one should keep in mind this is only on paper,
the danger is to get the wrong mindset: &lt;strong&gt;think of yourself as a single person
carrying a project, not an employee&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People often argue that they have a research director, who is de facto their boss.
I don&amp;rsquo;t think this is the case, directors choose project proposals and people
to carry them out (the order of this choice varies). They choose to invest
time, effort and money from their structure into this person+project pair,
without dictating to the letter what the outcomes of the projects are.
Their retribution for this exchange is a partial ownership in the outcomes
of the project (publications, conferences, software).
Sounds familiar? Yes I&amp;rsquo;m looking at the Wikipedia
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Venture_capital&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;page on Venture Capital&lt;/a&gt;.
Let&amp;rsquo;s dig deeper: thesis directors invest this time, money and energy in
areas they are familiar with, they have worked in and/or have mentored other
people on. This sounds like the VC firms&amp;rsquo; investment theses.
Read &lt;a href=&#34;https://a16z.com/2016/08/20/why-software-is-eating-the-world/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;these&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://hackernoon.com/the-birth-of-a-venture-capital-investment-thesis-afd2903ae12&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;two&lt;/a&gt;
articles to see a more proper definition and examples of investment theses
but I hope you&amp;rsquo;ll get my point: PhDs are not R&amp;amp;D employees and directors are
not &amp;ldquo;bosses&amp;rdquo;. If you have friends familiar with how startups work, this should
be fine to explain. If you&amp;rsquo;re talking to people who have been employees their
whole life in traditional structures, I have not yet found a clear and simple
way to explain the situation in a casual conversation, let me know if you have
something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;so-back-to-being-a-student-heh&#34;&gt;So, back to being a student heh?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This image is much easier to correct. On the paper this is true,
a PhD has a student status, even when working close with/in
companies like in Germany, Denmark or France CIFRE theses.
Some people will ask this genuinely because they still picture their
undergraduate years and think you&amp;rsquo;re back to this.
So, it&amp;rsquo;s true, I&amp;rsquo;m taking courses, mostly because I find them
interesting and keeping learning things is a bit of a &lt;em&gt;raison d&amp;rsquo;être&lt;/em&gt;.
But I was also doing so while working, using online courses platform like
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Coursera&lt;/a&gt; or
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fun-mooc.fr/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;France Université Numérique&lt;/a&gt;, going to meetups,
reading and writing blog posts. So the thing that changed is maybe the part
of my time dedicated to learning which got higher than when employed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now about the second category of people asking this question, yeah those one.
In general, the points discussed above are enough as an explanation,
but if the tone is really about trolling, which can happen, reverse the question:
&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Yeah I&amp;rsquo;m a student, I&amp;rsquo;m learning stuff every day. Wait you&amp;rsquo;re not?
Exactly the stagnation I don&amp;rsquo;t want in my life.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it mean? Maybe, but the point is not to &amp;ldquo;win&amp;rdquo; a conversation, it&amp;rsquo;s about
shutting down the perpetration of imposter syndrome, own the uniqueness of
your status, both the good and the bad bits. None should be made feel inferior
because they didn&amp;rsquo;t take the conventional, safe and socially accepted path of
the 9-17 workday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;re-thinking-my-values-priorities&#34;&gt;Re-thinking my values &amp;amp; priorities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve written about values &lt;a href=&#34;https://matbesancon.github.io/post/2016-10-7-company-values/&#34;&gt;two years ago&lt;/a&gt;
in the context of a company trying to define who they are.
This is a complex topic, about discovering and understanding what the
group prioritizes collectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the owner of your project and of your time and resources, it&amp;rsquo;s up to you to define
what is important. This begins with what is measured for success. Coming to academia
from another &lt;em&gt;milieu&lt;/em&gt;, I was not used to the process of publishing in peer-reviewed
journals. First position I&amp;rsquo;ll take and try to maintain: &lt;strong&gt;the measures of academic
success are broken, or at least imperfect&lt;/strong&gt; (reach out to future-me if I change my mind).
One example of this is research software.
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Paraphrasing &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mgymrek?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@mgymrek&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Your paper is cited outside of your field in one semi-related paragraph: *counts towards your career progression*&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Your academic software package has 100 stars on GitHub: *counts for nothing*&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Something is wrong here 😐 &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/jsm2018?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#jsm2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Sean Kross 🍋🌴 (@seankross) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/seankross/status/1024059834654588929?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 30, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Had my &amp;quot;software is part of the research process&amp;quot; argument with an academic who wanted to use software to generate results but didn&amp;#39;t want to &amp;quot;concentrate on it too much&amp;quot;. I should start counting how many times I go through this and throw a party when I get to a million.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Simon Hettrick (@sjh5000) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/sjh5000/status/1043112943372644353?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;September 21, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

If you can, watch
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/walkingrandomly&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mike Croucher&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s excellent
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8ZSaAM8hhJ4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt; at JuliaCon 2018 for more
depth on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consequence of ignoring software as a valuable result of research is
pretty straight-forward: proprietary software all over.
It&amp;rsquo;s changing in scientific computing, statistics and other fields with
the rise of Julia, R, Python. My domain, mathematical optimization, is
still behind with dominant solvers (the software doing the actual work)
and lots of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Algebraic_modeling_language&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Algebraic Modeling Languages&lt;/a&gt;
(the front-end to interact with the solver) being proprietary.
The last part is &lt;a href=&#34;https://numfocus.org/project/jump&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;changing&lt;/a&gt;,
the first one is still tough.
My point is that people behind software you&amp;rsquo;re
using everyday contribute way more to the success of your PhD than this
obscure paper you cite because the review committee asked you to.
If your university is giving thousands in commercial licenses and
millions in access to paper, maybe you should make them donate both time
and money to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flipcause.com/secure/cause_pdetails/MjM2OA==&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;tools&lt;/a&gt;
you&amp;rsquo;re using. Yes all of &lt;a href=&#34;https://donate.wikimedia.org/wiki/WMFJA1/en/US&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;them&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been involved in the Julia community, especially within the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/JuliaGraphs/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;JuliaGraphs&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/JuliaStats/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;JuliaStats&lt;/a&gt; ecosystems, mostly because these
are subjects I understand (at least a bit) and/or used.
Key take-away:
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    You don&amp;rsquo;t need to be an expert programmer to help out
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reporting issues you have and contributing to improve the documentation
is as valuable as writing code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;so-it-s-been-a-year&#34;&gt;So&amp;hellip; it&amp;rsquo;s been a year&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I&amp;rsquo;m still learning (understand making mistakes, getting stuck, etc),
one of the reasons I had to learn more is not coming from a background
in maths, nor from a research-oriented degree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reach out any way you prefer, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/matbesancon&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://matbesancon.github.io/#contact&#34;&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;. Of course some things I&amp;rsquo;ve written are related
to my situation, I&amp;rsquo;d be interested to know how it relates or not to yours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image sources:&lt;br /&gt;
[1] &lt;a href=&#34;https://pxhere.com/en/photo/571187&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://pxhere.com/en/photo/571187&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[2] &lt;a href=&#34;https://pixabay.com/en/noodles-thailand-food-thai-2693009/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://pixabay.com/en/noodles-thailand-food-thai-2693009/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
