<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>startup on μβ</title>
    <link>https://matbesancon.github.io/tags/startup/</link>
    <description>Recent content in startup on μβ</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-ca</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019 Mathieu Besançon</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="https://matbesancon.github.io/tags/startup/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Company values: stop trying to dictate who you are</title>
      <link>https://matbesancon.github.io/post/2016-10-7-company-values/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://matbesancon.github.io/post/2016-10-7-company-values/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago, the Equisense &lt;a href=&#34;http://equisense.com/en/about.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;team&lt;/a&gt; spent a
couple days together near the ocean in northern France. The goal was to get to
know each other better and sit down to (re)think on the way we work, where we
are heading and try to put some words on who we are and how we plan on moving
forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You named it, we tried to define one of the obsessions in the startup culture:
company values. There are many pitfalls to avoid while doing so and any of them
can make the company look as a cliché, under-ambitious or reject some of the
stakeholders. Keep in mind that these values are publicly displayed or at least
talked about, which means your employees, investors and clients could all feel
disconnected from them. At best, their reaction would be
&amp;ldquo;whatever, I guess everybody says so&amp;rdquo; and see you as another cliché.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At worst, they can reject the way you define yourself and consider the
advantages of working with you are not worth it.
But is the second scenario really worse? The scope of such problem is a lot
wider than your external communication and the &amp;ldquo;values&amp;rdquo; tab of your website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using Paul Graham&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.paulgraham.com/growth.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;definition&lt;/a&gt;,
a startup is all about growth, hence moving
fast. Quick decisions and executions cannot come without breaking things and
building tension on the way. Trying to define values because they make you
sound confident while being agreeable by everyone cannot yield any outcome.
No great result comes out of willing to please everyone, and the corollary is
that &lt;strong&gt;every successful person and organization has haters&lt;/strong&gt;. Given this
statement, the best any entity can do is to choose who is likely not to stick
with them and why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-values-anyway&#34;&gt;Why values anyway?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This question is totally legit, especially in countries like France where the
startup culture is still not familiar to a significant part of the population
or like Germany where pragmatism is king in both what you do and how you
communicate it.
Traditional organizations have always had a simple deal on the recruitment side:
lend me your skills and I&amp;rsquo;ll pay you decently. On the clients&amp;rsquo; side, the
&amp;ldquo;values&amp;rdquo; displayed were traditionally associated with product differentiation
(&amp;ldquo;at XYZ, our obsession is to bring the best product to [insert target] at
unbeatable prices&amp;rdquo;).
The shareholders&amp;rsquo; side did not even need big words, a couple KPIs from the last
quarter would do. As &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@Nicolas_Colin&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Nicolas Colin&lt;/a&gt; phrases
in several Medium posts, keeping what is being said to each of these
stakeholders completely separated is not possible anymore in the digital age.
That&amp;rsquo;s partly why company&amp;rsquo;s culture and values became central topics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve seen two cases at traditional companies. The first situation is ignorance
or non-existence of company values, maybe some of these will sound familiar:
&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Values? No this is the communication staff&amp;rsquo;s business&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;We&amp;rsquo;re not here to dream, we&amp;rsquo;re paid to get the job done&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second attitude is picking up &amp;ldquo;values&amp;rdquo; corresponding to trends but
completely disconnected from the organization&amp;rsquo;s reality. Just visit the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://cbsg.sf.net&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Corporate bullshit generator&lt;/a&gt; and you will know what I&amp;rsquo;m
referring to:
We&amp;rsquo;ve all seen extremely conservative companies call themselves &amp;ldquo;innovators&amp;rdquo;
or some historical monopolists call themselves &amp;ldquo;disruptive&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what changed with startups? Simple, you can redefine the way your market
works (and sometimes create it in the process) and become the central element
for it. That&amp;rsquo;s an idea you can genuinely believe in, work for and something you
can promise employees, shareholders and clients.
Now where are your values in this? Simply where you want the market to go and
the path you&amp;rsquo;re ready to take to go there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are obviously other factors at stake here, the fact that millennials
need to define themselves through what they do for instance and cannot just
work for a decent paycheck in the same polite colleague relation for 40+ years.
More than ever, our generation needs some sense in what we do at the moment and
not in a 40-year projection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;writing-down-values-is-about-choosing-a-path-and-sticking-to-it&#34;&gt;Writing down values is about choosing a path and sticking to it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d say this is the main highlight I got from hours of thoughts about the topic
of company values. &lt;strong&gt;Choosing values is not about sounding cool&lt;/strong&gt;, not about
the image you want for the organization&amp;rsquo;s recruitments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something concrete? Don&amp;rsquo;t define yourself as hackers if you spend at least as
much time planning as actually trying and building stuff. Don&amp;rsquo;t pretend to
disrupt anything if you&amp;rsquo;re playing the old rules within a known and stable
market. Don&amp;rsquo;t define yourself as transparent if you&amp;rsquo;re not obsessed with
everyone knowing both how you think and operate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defining yourself through the most trendy terms of the year has lead to a
feeling of emptiness in the messages carried in the startup ecosystems and has
even become one of its
&lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.caranddriver.com/2016-consumer-electronics-show-cutting-through-the-buzzwords-to-what-really-matters/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;clichés&lt;/a&gt;
or even &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=J-GVd_HLlps&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;jokes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-define-your-company-in-a-non-cliché-way&#34;&gt;How to define your company in a non-cliché way&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won&amp;rsquo;t have the pretension to set the rules on this point, simply to match
some great frameworks from people smarter than me who gave this point
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MpVCQfImQ1A&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;years of thoughts&lt;/a&gt;
(conference in French by Oussama Ammar) with the annoying points we discussed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Start with the hard way: define the cool things you are not. This goes with
a conclusion drawn earlier, every successful organization has haters, but don’t
get the cause-effect relation wrong: your company is not going to reach its
goals once it has haters. It should have haters because it defined a clear path
to success which induced not satisfying every stakeholder on the way. The
corollary is even a stronger conclusion: trying to please every potential
target and stakeholder is the safest way to getting stuck and unable to make
any decision. This is a luxury startups cannot afford by definition. Immobility
can only be explainable in traditional and established businesses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Define your values on the fly: just like you don’t decide as a child that
you are a nice person, you don’t decide as a company that you are disrupters
before living it. Discover your organization as you are working together and
reaching the first painful milestones, these key steps in your development when
you have to decide where priorities are being set and who is not going to
remain supportive afterwards. These tough experiences and the retrospective
understanding of your reaction as a team will make you more confident in what
you are doing and help cut the fluff on things you are not meant to do.
This is the focus everyone needs to move faster and sharper than the
competition, the market and the context.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back to startup life: thoughts after the first days</title>
      <link>https://matbesancon.github.io/post/2016-08-11-back-to-startup/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://matbesancon.github.io/post/2016-08-11-back-to-startup/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;In politics, a government&amp;rsquo;s first decisions and actions are often reviewed and
assessed after the famous first 100 days. According to &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First_hundred_days&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;,
the term was coined by F. Roosevelt himself. I wanted to throw the first
thoughts on my comeback at Equisense, on culture and operations and the difference
between the two stages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;startups-are-in-a-continuous-headlong-rush&#34;&gt;Startups are in a continuous headlong rush&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll not wait the 100 days to write this post, because in a startup things move
faster, so why wait another month? At the same time you have to remain focused
for a lot longer than three months or the consequences to expect are worse than
skeptical articles or plunging opinion polls. Nobody could judge actions or
decisions drawn after a year in business based on one or even three months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this adrenalined marathon does not (or should not) stop with a first product
release, or worse with a nice fund-raising round. This stops with the company
running out of business or the market saying &amp;ldquo;I love you, let&amp;rsquo;s stay forever
until death do us apart&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;an-early-insight-before-the-long-break&#34;&gt;An early insight before the long break&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had already worked with the team in June, July and August 2015 during their
three-founders-and-laptops stage. The focus was on first studies of acceleration
signals and feasibility of some features given technological and product choices.
Those first graphs and explanations thrown on a small Tex reports
were later improved and re-written by the team as it designed
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.equisense.com/en/product.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Motion&lt;/a&gt;. After these few months,
I left the startup for Montréal, where I spent my last semester as a student,
after which I carried out my Master project in Germany. When came the time to
think about what came next, we were still in contact with Camille, Idriss and
Benoit and the conversation shifted to how the project had evolved and the
thousand cool things coming in the next months and could become a &amp;ldquo;real job&amp;rdquo;
this time. After a couple more one-to-one, a few visits in Lille and a hackathon,
I was officially back on the adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;getting-back-and-the-baby-is-all-grown-up&#34;&gt;Getting back and the baby is all grown up!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, Equisense launched a successful Kickstarter, reinforcing the
feeling that horse-riders value what the product can bring to their experience.
The company moved from its first office in Compiègne Innovation Center to
the impressive Euratechnologies center in Lille.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://matbesancon.github.io/img/posts/100Days/euratechnologies.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Euratechnologies&#34; /&gt;
[1]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than this, the team also got bigger to face the challenges of this new
stage. The goal is no longer to hack horses acceleration signals until something
comes out of it, but to build a reliable and intuitive product from the
scientific findings and technological pieces brought together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really getting on the market requires a deeper bond with horse-riders
and as much feedback as possible. The new team embodies these changes: a
diversity of mindsets, experiences and backgrounds to handle all upcoming
challenges with the same care for clients. The hacker spirit isn&amp;rsquo;t gone in
this new version of the company, but it isn&amp;rsquo;t the major pillar of the culture
anymore. A culture is hard to put into words, but I&amp;rsquo;d say this
second face of our Janus startup is a combination of a &lt;strong&gt;genuine care for
horses wellness and of a passion for horse-riding.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://matbesancon.github.io/img/posts/100Days/newteam.png&#34; alt=&#34;The new team&#34; /&gt;
[2]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact is that while I was admiring their external successes from my Canadian
home, (the Kickstarter campaign, new partnerships, features of the product
getting out of the ground one by one&amp;hellip;), the most impressive achievement was
being joined by so many diverse profiles while building a working environment
at the image of their horse-riders&amp;rsquo; mindset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The founders already had this care and passion in their DNA, they just
succeeded in transforming it into a full culture and transmitting it into an
obsession within the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://matbesancon.github.io/img/posts/100Days/camille.png&#34; alt=&#34;Camille&#34; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://matbesancon.github.io/img/posts/100Days/benoit.png&#34; alt=&#34;Benoit&#34; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://matbesancon.github.io/img/posts/100Days/idriss.png&#34; alt=&#34;Idriss&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;where-are-we-in-the-lifetime-from-a-clumsy-foal-to-the-great-stallion&#34;&gt;Where are we in the lifetime? From a clumsy foal to the great stallion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than the culture, the operations changed from the clumsy foal learning to
stay up on its hoofs to the stallion swiftly jumping and anticipating all
obstacles.
&lt;img src=&#34;https://matbesancon.github.io/img/posts/100Days/foal.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;foal&#34; /&gt;
[3]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The seed stage is about using all assets that are or can easily
be at your disposal to run tests and confirm hypotheses. Unlike lots of web
startups, uncertainty does not come only from the market, but also from
the technological bricks: &lt;strong&gt;hardware is today where the web was about ten years
ago&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving forwards meant iterating while building knowledge on both fields of
uncertainty. This meant at the same time assessing if some measured signals
could detect a jump during a training session, and if the customers actually
had an interest in the feature. Working for nothing can be frustrating, but
ignoring something horse-riders want would have been much worse!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://matbesancon.github.io/img/posts/100Days/cso_fontainebleau.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;grown-up champ&#34; /&gt;
[5]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the new phase, uncertainty radically changed. In the first stage,
we saw how it was caused by a lack of knowledge on both the
technology and the market. Of course the knowledge the team has on
these topics is still not complete, but
&lt;strong&gt;is enough to make intelligent decisions and move on&lt;/strong&gt;. However, a
new source of uncertainty has replaced the two previous:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organization and processes are obvious when 4 people are working
together on several issues. They become fuzzy and chaotic when several
teams are working at high speed without being able to check on each
other all day long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key issue is the company&amp;rsquo;s speed to deliver
without letting any randomness in the result. Equisense&amp;rsquo;s customers
are horse-riders willing to improve their experience, care and
efficiency, not hackers accepting a buggy beta with promising
features as long as the product has an API in their favorite language!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equisense changed a lot during my absence to evolve into one of the new
major phenomena in its industry. If I had to describe how it operates
now, I guess I&amp;rsquo;d highlight &lt;strong&gt;the focus, the acceleration and the
deterministic, well-defined outcome of a still random and flexible organization&lt;/strong&gt;.
(hope my data science buddies will tolerate the paradox of the last one).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coming months promise to be thrilling with the shipping of the first Motion
sensors, the R&amp;amp;D on improved features, new products and whatever else comes
out of the blue. Even though I&amp;rsquo;m still getting used to working with horses (photos
to come), I&amp;rsquo;m without a doubt excited to have rejoined these crazy riders, so
stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image sources:
[1] &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lesechos.fr/politique-societe/regions/0203756306258-nord-pas-de-calais-a-lille-nait-la-silicon-valley-du-numerique-1043082.php&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Les Echos: Nord - Pas-de-Calais : A Lille naît la « Silicon Valley » du numérique&lt;/a&gt;
[2] &lt;a href=&#34;www.equisense.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Equisense website&lt;/a&gt;
[3] &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eco121.fr/equisense-ouvre-la-voie-du-cheval-connecte/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://www.eco121.fr/equisense-ouvre-la-voie-du-cheval-connecte/&lt;/a&gt;
[4] [5] Wikimedia&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On startup weekends and getting things done</title>
      <link>https://matbesancon.github.io/post/2016-07-11-hackathon/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://matbesancon.github.io/post/2016-07-11-hackathon/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s monday morning and I&amp;rsquo;m waking up with a hangover sensation, not from
partying in the streets of Lille as one could think at the beginning of the
week, but from the last intense 48 hours. I took part in the so-called
&amp;ldquo;creathon&amp;rdquo; organized by the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://switchupchallenge.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Switch up challenge&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;makesense.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MakeSense&lt;/a&gt;. The special touch on this event was the social
impact the projects were meant to have. The result could even not be a company
but a non-profit organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to generalize my thoughts as much as possible, but to give a
concrete view of what is going on, I&amp;rsquo;m going to use the example of &lt;strong&gt;Quare&lt;/strong&gt;,
the project we worked on. It is a device quantifying your stress and the quality
of your current working environment thanks to different sensors and
individually adjusted algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;building-a-company-from-the-ground-up-just-let-me-finish-this&#34;&gt;Building a company from the ground up: just let me finish this&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating the whole concept for a scalable, repeatable and profitable business
based on an issue you want to tackle takes time, focus and creativity. The goal
is not to come up with the most spectacular way to solve the problem and build
your product, but to find the simplest way allowing your business to grow
without limits. &lt;strong&gt;You&amp;rsquo;re not building the Empire State, you&amp;rsquo;re planting an
acorn to grow an oak&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;stop-organizing-everything-mess-is-a-bless&#34;&gt;Stop organizing everything, mess is a bless&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People coming from a business and management background tend to think of
activities in terms of processes, so a structured way in which things are
handled and operated. When designing the concept for a startup, just don&amp;rsquo;t.
The reason is, your team is going through several critical phases where any
constraint in the reasoning would hinder the ability to rephrase the problem
you&amp;rsquo;re focused on, or come up with a radical new way to address it. Just let
the mess happen and collectively feel when it is time to move on to a next step.
If a team member feels like you missed something, simply let them gather their
thoughts and arguments, then try to build on them and see how they change
the concept. However, not everything must be kept if you don&amp;rsquo;t want an
&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.dave-bailey.com/how-to-reconnect-with-your-purpose-as-a-founder-6d18e80ccc9c#.j39hta9i6&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;over-generalized problem&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;focus-is-key-to-deliver&#34;&gt;Focus is key to deliver&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This part is a bit tricky and you won&amp;rsquo;t find any silver bullet, even less in
this blog post. By focused, understand both being focus as state-of-mind and
keeping your business idea focused on what matters the most to the issue you
address: this is about making real choices which will never please everyone.
Keeping focused and moving fast during the week-end has two
effects. If you play well, &lt;strong&gt;you&amp;rsquo;ll deliver a lot more by the time of the final
pitch&lt;/strong&gt;, and that&amp;rsquo;s an awesome point if you have some of the following
objectives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convince and impress specific people in the room: potential partners, investors, accelerators&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check how comfortable team members are with each other, if you align on your
ambition, your definition and perception of the problem, the way you work and
react under pressure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To relate things to our situation this weekend, we were an initial team of two
engineers working for a middle-stage startup and two designers at ease with both
product and graphical design. A highly motivated business school student joined
the team a bit later in the weekend. We had both a creative and chaotic
enthusiasm to explore the problems related to stress and lack of focus at work
(the issue we decided to tackle) and some ability to focus and to move fast
based on our diverse experiences and skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We addressed the issue of focus at work which is our direct concern while
working in an open-space and dealing with creative work requiring long,
uninterrupted sessions to make the best out of a day.
Even though we spent a great deal of time defining the scope of the
problem and primary targets, we all had this &lt;em&gt;get things done&lt;/em&gt; attitude and
were eager to start realizing something concrete from the beginning. So not
only did we all have a strong link to the problem, we also had a common view on
it, it allowed the team to have a sharp vision and homogeneous of work and focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are also several not-so-good reasons to move fast during a startup
weekend:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Validate technical choices (Should my device communicate through Wifi or
Bluetooth? What information do we need to store from our clients? &lt;strong&gt;Any&lt;/strong&gt;
back-end related question)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Precise quantitative estimates are pointless. Yup, business plans don&amp;rsquo;t have
their place at a startup weekend, if they have a place at all for early stage
of uncertain and radically new businesses. Try to simply get some rough ideas
about the size of the problem, how much would the device cost in production.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, to relate this to our situation, we could make a pretty good estimate of
the Bill of Materials based on the sensors we wanted to use and on our
experience with Equisense (what components were needed, the type of
micro-controller, etc&amp;hellip;). We could come out with different shapes for the
device and test it thanks to different people giving feedback which allowed us
to iterate, but that was is. We did not go any further on the economic
projections, nor did we try to build the whole product in two days. Okay maybe
we prototyped the product with an Arduino and the appropriate sensors. That was
clearly unnecessary for the weekend, but still fun to
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/SophieDuveau/status/795248595301703681&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;play around&lt;/a&gt; with
hardware and show what anyone can do with a board, two sensors and some cables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, one of the team&amp;rsquo;s designers bought an Arduino kit right after the
weekend, a business student decided to go further with one of his personal
projects after seeing how much we had got done after two days.
Even if we don&amp;rsquo;t build the next unicorn, discovering each other&amp;rsquo;s fields and
building a common culture in so little time was in itself a success and a
learning experience.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
