<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Startup on μβ</title>
    <link>https://mbesancon.github.io/tags/startup/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Startup on μβ</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Mathieu Besançon</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2016 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/startup/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>On startup weekends and getting things done</title>
      <link>https://mbesancon.github.io/posts/2016-07-11-hackathon/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mbesancon.github.io/posts/2016-07-11-hackathon/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s monday morning and I&amp;rsquo;m waking up with a hangover sensation, not from
partying in the streets of Lille as one could think at the beginning of the
week, but from the last intense 48 hours. I took part in the so-called
&amp;ldquo;creathon&amp;rdquo; organized by the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://switchupchallenge.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Switch up challenge&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;makesense.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MakeSense&lt;/a&gt;. The special touch on this event was the social
impact the projects were meant to have. The result could even not be a company
but a non-profit organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to generalize my thoughts as much as possible, but to give a
concrete view of what is going on, I&amp;rsquo;m going to use the example of &lt;strong&gt;Quare&lt;/strong&gt;,
the project we worked on. It is a device quantifying your stress and the quality
of your current working environment thanks to different sensors and
individually adjusted algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;building-a-company-from-the-ground-up-just-let-me-finish-this&#34;&gt;Building a company from the ground up: just let me finish this&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating the whole concept for a scalable, repeatable and profitable business
based on an issue you want to tackle takes time, focus and creativity. The goal
is not to come up with the most spectacular way to solve the problem and build
your product, but to find the simplest way allowing your business to grow
without limits. &lt;strong&gt;You&amp;rsquo;re not building the Empire State, you&amp;rsquo;re planting an
acorn to grow an oak&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;stop-organizing-everything-mess-is-a-bless&#34;&gt;Stop organizing everything, mess is a bless&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People coming from a business and management background tend to think of
activities in terms of processes, so a structured way in which things are
handled and operated. When designing the concept for a startup, just don&amp;rsquo;t.
The reason is, your team is going through several critical phases where any
constraint in the reasoning would hinder the ability to rephrase the problem
you&amp;rsquo;re focused on, or come up with a radical new way to address it. Just let
the mess happen and collectively feel when it is time to move on to a next step.
If a team member feels like you missed something, simply let them gather their
thoughts and arguments, then try to build on them and see how they change
the concept. However, not everything must be kept if you don&amp;rsquo;t want an
&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.dave-bailey.com/how-to-reconnect-with-your-purpose-as-a-founder-6d18e80ccc9c#.j39hta9i6&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;over-generalized problem&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;focus-is-key-to-deliver&#34;&gt;Focus is key to deliver&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This part is a bit tricky and you won&amp;rsquo;t find any silver bullet, even less in
this blog post. By focused, understand both being focus as state-of-mind and
keeping your business idea focused on what matters the most to the issue you
address: this is about making real choices which will never please everyone.
Keeping focused and moving fast during the week-end has two
effects. If you play well, &lt;strong&gt;you&amp;rsquo;ll deliver a lot more by the time of the final
pitch&lt;/strong&gt;, and that&amp;rsquo;s an awesome point if you have some of the following
objectives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convince and impress specific people in the room: potential partners, investors, accelerators&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check how comfortable team members are with each other, if you align on your
ambition, your definition and perception of the problem, the way you work and
react under pressure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To relate things to our situation this weekend, we were an initial team of two
engineers working for a middle-stage startup and two designers at ease with both
product and graphical design. A highly motivated business school student joined
the team a bit later in the weekend. We had both a creative and chaotic
enthusiasm to explore the problems related to stress and lack of focus at work
(the issue we decided to tackle) and some ability to focus and to move fast
based on our diverse experiences and skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We addressed the issue of focus at work which is our direct concern while
working in an open-space and dealing with creative work requiring long,
uninterrupted sessions to make the best out of a day.
Even though we spent a great deal of time defining the scope of the
problem and primary targets, we all had this &lt;em&gt;get things done&lt;/em&gt; attitude and
were eager to start realizing something concrete from the beginning. So not
only did we all have a strong link to the problem, we also had a common view on
it, it allowed the team to have a sharp vision and homogeneous of work and focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are also several not-so-good reasons to move fast during a startup
weekend:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Validate technical choices (Should my device communicate through Wifi or
Bluetooth? What information do we need to store from our clients? &lt;strong&gt;Any&lt;/strong&gt;
back-end related question)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Precise quantitative estimates are pointless. Yup, business plans don&amp;rsquo;t have
their place at a startup weekend, if they have a place at all for early stage
of uncertain and radically new businesses. Try to simply get some rough ideas
about the size of the problem, how much would the device cost in production.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, to relate this to our situation, we could make a pretty good estimate of
the Bill of Materials based on the sensors we wanted to use and on our
experience with Equisense (what components were needed, the type of
micro-controller, etc&amp;hellip;). We could come out with different shapes for the
device and test it thanks to different people giving feedback which allowed us
to iterate, but that was is. We did not go any further on the economic
projections, nor did we try to build the whole product in two days. Okay maybe
we prototyped the product with an Arduino and the appropriate sensors. That was
clearly unnecessary for the weekend, but still fun to
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/SophieDuveau/status/795248595301703681&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;play around&lt;/a&gt; with
hardware and show what anyone can do with a board, two sensors and some cables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, one of the team&amp;rsquo;s designers bought an Arduino kit right after the
weekend, a business student decided to go further with one of his personal
projects after seeing how much we had got done after two days.
Even if we don&amp;rsquo;t build the next unicorn, discovering each other&amp;rsquo;s fields and
building a common culture in so little time was in itself a success and a
learning experience.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
