<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Authors on μβ</title>
    <link>https://matbesancon.github.io/authors/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Authors on μβ</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-ca</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; {year} Mathieu Besançon</copyright>
    
	    <atom:link href="https://matbesancon.github.io/authors/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://matbesancon.github.io/authors/admin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://matbesancon.github.io/authors/admin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am a PhD candidate in a double program (&lt;em&gt;cotutelle&lt;/em&gt;) between
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.polymtl.ca&#34;&gt;École Polytechnique of Montréal&lt;/a&gt;,
at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gerad.ca/en/&#34;&gt;GERAD lab&lt;/a&gt; and
Centrale Lille, at &lt;a href=&#34;https://team.inria.fr/inocs&#34;&gt;INRIA&lt;/a&gt;
&amp;amp; the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cristal.univ-lille.fr/?lang=en&#34;&gt;Cristal&lt;/a&gt; lab,
in mathematical optimization for pricing applications in smart grids.
I am currently on an academic visit at the School of Mathematics at the University of Edinburgh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My thesis focuses on bilevel optimization, robust extensions
and pricing for demand response. Other topics I look at include
non-linear optimization &amp;amp; applications in engineering,
integer optimization &amp;amp; decompositions, game theory and optimization applications in statistics &amp;amp; learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am involved in several open-source projects around optimization and
scientific computing, mostly in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://julialang.org&#34;&gt;Julia&lt;/a&gt; programming language.
Before starting the PhD, I worked in various industries, from an IoT startup to steel
manufacturing. I did my joint Bachelor-Master in Process Engineering at
the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.utc.fr&#34;&gt;UTC&lt;/a&gt; with a semester at
the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tu-braunschweig.de/?lang=en&#34;&gt;TUBS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a personal note, I read both fiction (mostly detective, thrillers and fantasy)
and non-fiction books, generally on economic policy, strategy
and entrepreneurship (a more detailed list can be found on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/review/list/110133896&#34;&gt;goodread&lt;/a&gt;.
I also games in various formats (tabletop, video, board, card).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I will be looking for a position to start in 2021.&lt;/strong&gt;
Although I am primarily looking at positions in academic environments and research institutes,
I am open to research-intensive environments with projects on the topics mentioned above.
My academic CV is available upon request.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
