<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>economics on μβ</title>
    <link>https://matbesancon.github.io/tags/economics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in economics on μβ</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-ca</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019 Mathieu Besançon</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="https://matbesancon.github.io/tags/economics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Book review: the Entrepreneurial State</title>
      <link>https://matbesancon.github.io/post/2019-01-24-entrepreneurial-state-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://matbesancon.github.io/post/2019-01-24-entrepreneurial-state-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While reading books, lots of thoughts come and go, especially if the subject
resonates and is connected to topics of interest. If the book is a
novel or other fiction, I try to keep these thoughts away to remain in the
universe and story. For non-fiction though, some of these thoughts constitute
valuable elements to put on a larger frame, with other publications, slowly building
context for the topics at hand. The &lt;strong&gt;Entrepreneurial State&lt;/strong&gt;, by
Mariana Mazzucato, definitely has some elements to put on a larger frame
of economic policy, economics, on the perceived and actual role of the state
and its institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;changing-the-narrative&#34;&gt;Changing the narrative&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main point and argument of the book is brilliant: re-trace the facts
about the development of some technologies, companies, industries to challenge
the established, implicit or explicit narrative about the state&amp;rsquo;s role.
In that case, the narrative is the sacred effect of the market and individual
entrepreneurs for building today&amp;rsquo;s greatest achievements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-unexpected-hr-argument&#34;&gt;The unexpected HR argument&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One point I never thought about before reading the book is the talent pool each
side is taking from. While keeping the sexy part of the narrative, the private
firms will always attract the best talents. For sure, some people will join
public services for the greater good, but some necessary talents might not
join because they have major criteria on what to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the narrative is that public institutions are there simply for controlling
and punctually fixing the economy, lots of talents will be driven by private
firms able to offer them to actually accomplish things and move forward.
If the State is now seen as the voice setting the direction for the coming
years and the rules to get there before letting the children out on the
playground, people working in the &amp;ldquo;development department&amp;rdquo; as Mazzucato calls
it play a part in a strategic role they would not have in the firms themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you think about it, the only public servants glorified and pictured with
cool jobs in today&amp;rsquo;s representation are linked to the military or police.
Think of recent corporate series you&amp;rsquo;ve seen, public servants are always those
envious ones who didn&amp;rsquo;t have the courage to take the risky path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;oh-no-apple-again&#34;&gt;Oh no, Apple again&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To add some context, the first edition of the book was out in 2013. If I
try to remember the ambient perception, tech was not yet the evil eating the
world, building a startup was still freaking your parents out
(at least if you lived in France), Bitcoin was still nerds&amp;rsquo; or drugs money.
And Apple was still in the general opinion the cool company building slick products.
A chapter of the book is specifically dedicated to the company and how it has
been helped by the US federal and state governments at various stages and for
various steps of its rise. The narrative the author sets is that &lt;strong&gt;even&lt;/strong&gt; the
most innovative, &amp;ldquo;entrepreneurial&amp;rdquo;, garage-born companies got helped by the
government all the way through, whatever version of it is told by them,
the media or VCs. Still, this is a personal touch, but Apple has never been
fascinating, nor have I admired the firm more than others, or had this &amp;ldquo;wow&amp;rdquo;
effect to friends getting jobs there. It&amp;rsquo;s still a consumer firm building
expensive toys, not solving the world&amp;rsquo;s problem. The problem with this chapter
is that I agreed with the author&amp;rsquo;s underlying point before even starting it,
so the content I read felt mostly like a bunch of historical facts on a company
I am not that interested in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;changing-energy-systems&#34;&gt;Changing energy systems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently involved in a PhD involving thinking new decision processes for power
grids, I naturally got thrilled to see a chapter on renewable generation
and green business. The author mentions the parallel and applications of
IT to these new challenges, with the nice mention of
&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;throwing software at the problem&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; [1], referring to designing algorithms
to cope with solar and wind power intermittency.
In that case, it is indeed necessary but not sufficient. Software will at
most bring information within reach of the agents needing it at the right time.
This availability is only a prerequisite for enabling better decision-making in power systems,
creating value shared between the different levels contributing to the
various improvements. See recent work in journals such as IEEE Transactions on
Power Systems / on Smart Grids, the hard problems are not data collection or
transmission but making decision under various types of constraints.
Nonetheless, it was a nice surprise to read an economist&amp;rsquo;s view, summary
and prediction for smart grids, with mentions of programs such as demand response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-danger-of-the-strawman&#34;&gt;The danger of the strawman&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This might be one central critic to the book, from an argument construction
perspective. The whole stream of thought is built around a de- and reconstruction
of the role of the State for major innovations, past and present. There is
however the continuous danger of a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Straw_man&#34;&gt;strawman argument&lt;/a&gt;,
the detractors of the role of the states are often described as &amp;ldquo;they&amp;rdquo;, and
referred to vaguely compared to other topics for which the author provides
numerous references. In comparison, re-using the same article from
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.economist.com/leaders/2012/04/21/the-third-industrial-revolution&#34;&gt;the Economist&lt;/a&gt;
for the other side of the argument seems like an unfair trial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;going-further-other-critical-angles&#34;&gt;Going further, other critical angles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have one take-away from this post, the book is worth reading in depth
and thinking over. It strikes a nice balance between the academic rigour,
providing plenty of references to go further on different topics and developing
arguments with care, while staying pleasant to read before going to bed, during
your commute or with your favourite cup of Earl Grey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not being an economist, I will not go far in comparison to other schools of
thought on industrial and innovation policies.
Feel free to check &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forbes.com/sites/timworstall/2013/12/15/the-intellectual-hole-at-the-heart-of-mariana-mazzucatos-entrepreneurial-state/#6042744d728b&#34;&gt;those&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.questia.com/library/journal/1G1-432806536/a-critique-of-mazzucato-s-entrepreneurial-state&#34;&gt;other&lt;/a&gt;
articles shedding another light on the ideas developed in the book for critical
points of view but mostly
&lt;a href=&#34;https://salon.thefamily.co/innovation-doesnt-run-on-calls-for-projects-4f878ca8e31&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;
excellent summary and analysis by Nicolas Colin, whose book
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Nicolas_Colin/status/1014439870524215302&#34;&gt;Hedge&lt;/a&gt; is next
on my reading list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to reach out any way you prefer, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/matbesancon&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://matbesancon.github.io/#contact&#34;&gt;email&lt;/a&gt; to exchange or discuss the book or this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sources&#34;&gt;Sources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] &amp;ldquo;Powering the Dream: The History and Promise of Green Technology&amp;rdquo; Madrigal, 2011&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
